Preliminary Inventory to the Keith Middlemas collection
Hoover Institution Archives
Keith Middlemas collection
1966-1994
77036
Hoover Institution Archives
15 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box (7.7 linear feet)
Sound recordings and written summaries of interviews with British, Portuguese and African diplomats, politicians, economic advisers, journalists, and businessmen, relating to the Portuguese revolution of 1974, revolutionary developments in Portuguese colonies, and other aspects of the political situation in southern Africa; Western European communist leaders, relating to the Eurocommunist movement in Western Europe; British civil servants and financial and trade union leaders, relating to British political and economic conditions; and European government officials, relating to the decision-making process in the European communities.
Middlemas, Keith, 1935-
Access
The collection is open for research. The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Scope and Contents note
Sound recordings and written summaries of interviews with British, Portuguese and African diplomats, politicians, economic advisers, journalists, and businessmen, relating to the Portuguese revolution of 1974, revolutionary developments in Portuguese colonies, and other aspects of the political situation in southern Africa; Western European communist leaders, relating to the Eurocommunist movement in Western Europe; British civil servants and financial and trade union leaders, relating to British political and economic conditions; and European government officials, relating to the decision-making process in the European communities.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1977.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Africa.; Angola--Politics and government.; Angola.; Communism--Europe.; Communism.; Europe--Economic conditions--1945-; Europe--Politics and government--1989-; Europe.; European communities.; Great Britain--Economic conditions--1945-; Great Britain--Politics and government--1945-; Great Britain.; Malawi.; Mozambique--Politics and government.; Mozambique.; Phonotapes.; Portugal--Colonies.; Portugal--History--Revolution, 1974.; Portugal.; South Africa.; Zambia.; Zimbabwe.
- PORTUGAL AND AFRICA (Group A)
  - Notes to tapes (Box 1)
    - A1
    - A2
    - A3-A4
    - A5
    - A6 (includes Malawi Government economic report, 1971)
    - A7
    - A8 (includes Act no. 22 of 1940: Industrial Development Corporation of South Africa)
    - A9
    - A10-A12
    - A13-A15
    - A16-A17
    - A18-A20
    - A21-A23
  - Documents (Box 2)
    - Envelopes 1-3
    - Envelopes 4-5 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous publications
    - Envelope 6
    - Envelopes 7-9 (Boxes 4, 16)
    - Envelopes 10-11 (Boxes 5, 16)
  - Writings, notes, bulletins, and printed matter (Box 6)
  - Tapes (Box 7)
    - A1, (1970-1971)
      - Dalton, Richard
      - Fontes e Falcao, Alfredo
      - Surry, John
      - Schoter, Hans
      - Niggel, Gunter
      - Pavlitski, E.
      - Seidel, W.
      - Haffa, Wolfgang
      - Green, Reginald
      - Chappelle, F.
      - Braga, Dr. A.
    - A2, (1971)
      - Braga, Dr. A.
      - Cavalho, Eduardo
      - Anderson, Garrett
      - Walford, Col. B.
      - Duncan, S.
      - Devaux, M.
      - Santos, Toni
      - Prune-Foch, M.
      - Fairweather, Patrick
      - Zeldine, Jean
      - FRELIMO official
      - Bossiere, M. la
      - Gastor, Polly
      - Mangani, Alessandro
    - A3-A4, (n.d.)
      - Mangani, Alessandro
      - Colleoni, G.
      - Fairweather, Patrick
      - Kaldor, Mary
      - Lemperiere, M.
      - Biche, Mme
      - Nogueira, Franco
      - Diaz da Cunha, Martin (spokesman for)
      - Rego, Raul
      - Cardoso Pires
      - Walford, Col.
      - Fernandes, Sergio
      - Hall, David
      - Magalhaes, Calvet de
      - British military attache, Lisbon
      - Ferreira, Mario
      - Bendixen, Bernard
      - Abreu, Jorge
      - Routh, Thelma
      - Carvalho, Claudo
      - Murupa, Miguel
      - Crespo, Mario
      - Crespo and other officers
      - Santos, Almeida
    - A5, (1971)
      - Santos, Almeida
      - Lagos, Sgt.
      - D'Arriaga, Kaulza
      - Morgado, Angelo
      - Marques de Abrantes Amaral, Dr.
      - Wilde
      - Free-Gore, Alan
      - McAllister, W.
      - Ginnari, Raphael
      - Costas, Victor
      - De Jesus, Fernando
      - Cartaxama, Rui
      - Interviews at Cabora Bassa
      - Chambers, William
      - Anderson, Garrett
      - Serra, Edwardo de
      - Smith, Bell
      - Jordan, Franz
      - Portuguese lieutenant
      - Indunas (head man) at Estima village
      - Swann, David
      - Fernandes, Sergio
      - Nunes, Nelson
      - Duncan, S.
      - Zenha, Salgado
      - Matello, J. M.
      - Bendixen, Bernard
      - Chambers, William
      - Brebant, Antoine
      - M'Tapa, Regedor (head man, Estima village)
      - Coutinho, Dr.
      - Gudinho, Eng.
      - Falcao, Eng.
      - Matsinhya, Mariano
      - Mendlame, Janet
    - A6, (1971)
      - Adviser to the Malawi Cabinet
      - Gumane, Paulo
      - Tembe, Lopes
      - Rebelo, Jorge
      - Wateridge, Alan
      - Blackwell, Leslie
      - Martin, Meredith
      - Reid, Martin
      - Green, Reginald
      - Mdee, Sammy
      - Kasonde
      - Mijone, Vincent
      - Manda, Raphael
      - Sardanis, Andrew
      - Nkolosi
      - Pereira, Vasco
      - Board, David
      - Representative of Escom (Malawi)
      - Pearson, Don
    - A7, (1971)
      - Treasury official, Malawi (not recorded)
      - Assistant to secretary of Malawi Treasury
      - British high commissioner, Malawi
      - Frensari
      - Goode, Richard
      - Adesola
      - Green, Reginald
      - Peirson, Mike
      - Silya Costa, F.
      - Martin, Meredith
      - Zucas, Simon
      - Fittington, David
      - Jaap-van-Velsen
      - Duncan, James
      - Micken, Joan
      - White, E.
      - Grinshaw, Edward
      - Brown, Irena
    - A8, (1971)
      - Ayres, James
      - Canadian doctor working in Tanzania
      - Oppenheimer, H. F.
      - Coulson, Mike
      - Dickman, Aubrey
      - Northey, Adrian
      - Jackson
      - Du Plessies, T. C.
      - Sanders, E.
      - Coulson and others
      - Kailey, Dennis
      - Norman, H. B.
      - Various
      - Vat, Dan van der
      - Olivier, Henry
    - A9, (n.d.)
      - Palmer, George
      - Morgan, Michael
      - Montgomery, F. G.
      - Brown, E. T. S.
      - Bowring, Col.
      - Hawkins, J.
      - Hooley
      - Keyser, Karl
      - Civil servant, Rhodesian Foreign Ministry
      - Welenskey, Sir Roy
      - Graylin, John
      - Unknown
      - Osborne
      - Staff reporter, Financial Mail, Johannesburg
      - Dickman, Aubrey
      - Ruche, Christian
      - Falcao e Cunha
      - Costa, Campus
      - Araujo, Anthony
      - Zenha, Salgado
    - A10, (1972-1973)
      - Zenha, Salgado
      - Byatt, Hugh
      - Fernandes, Sergio
      - Grennan, Dennis
      - Falcao, Dr.
      - Vigny, Alfred
      - Magalhaes, Calvet de
      - Figueiredo, Antonio de
      - Walford, Col.
      - Fontes, Castro
      - Military attache, British embassy, Paris
      - Diplomat
      - Diplomat
      - Diplomat, British embassy, Bonn
      - Olivier, Henry
      - Haffa, A.
      - Bossiere, M. la
      - Albert, H.
      - Unknown, of Siemens Co.
      - Precourt, Philipe de
      - Grenfell, Julian
    - A11-A12, (1973-1974)
      - Nigell, A.
      - Holmes, B.
      - Gierese
      - Lemperiere, Antoine
      - Bendixen, Bernard
      - Langer, Horst
      - Electrician, Hydroelectric work, Cabora Bassa
      - Brebant, E.
      - Jordan, F.
      - Chambers, William
      - Five headmen of the Shangaan, Cabora Bassa
      - Walford, Col.
      - Jardim, Jorge
      - Unknown
      - Fernandes, Sergio
      - Falcao e Cunha
      - Diplomat, Lisbon
      - Ferreira, Mario
      - Nogueira, Frank
      - Jordan, F.
      - Rodriges, C.
      - Crespo, Mario
      - Sousa, Crispin de
      - Oliveira, Braz d'
      - Oliveira and Fonseca
      - Diplomat, Lisbon
      - Edis, John
      - Abreau, Simeos
      - Duncan, S.
      - Abreu, Jorge
      - Fontes, Castro
      - Pereira, Lt.
      - Costa Lobo, Albano
      - Free-Gore, Alan
      - Diplomat, Lisbon
      - Pimental dos Santos
      - Spranger, L. C.
      - Sousa, Jaime de
      - Duncan, S.
      - Silva, Antunes de
      - Martins, O.
    - A13, (1974)
      - Mauricio, Dr.
      - Cartaxana, Rui
      - Caudo
      - Three officers in the Portuguese Army
      - Hansford, Mike
      - Dickman, Aubrey
      - Robinson, Sir Philip
      - Keyser, Karl
      - Katri, Gabriel
      - Palmer, George
      - Montgomery
      - Barrett, John
      - Krause, Otto
      - Diplomat, Pretoria
      - Killen, Rae
      - South African Chamber of Mines
      - Norman, E.
      - Olivier, Henry
      - Brown, E. T. S.
      - Vat, Dan van der
      - Shine, Harry
      - Hawkins, R.
      - Osborne, J.
      - Howlman, F.
      - Katri, Gabriel
      - Rupert, Anton
      - SAMEPCO
      - Matsanya, Marwano
    - A14, (1974)
      - Matsanya, Marwano
      - Gumane, Paulo
      - Sousa, Jaime de
      - ODA representative
      - Indebank, Malawi
      - Pumabantu
      - Zukas, S.
      - Crampin, C.
      - FRELIMO representative
      - Diplomat, Lusaka
      - Diplomat, Malawi
      - Proenca, J. M. da
      - Raynor, Gerald
      - Zambian agronomist
      - Diplomat, Lusaka
      - Diplomat, Lusaka
      - Diplomat, Lusaka
      - Diplomat, Dar es Salaam
      - Anglo-American representative in Zambia
      - British diplomat, London
      - Magalpine
      - British diplomat, London
      - Routh, Thelma
      - Sousa, Jaime de
      - Cook, Michael
      - Ferreira, Mario
    - A15, (1974) (Box 8)
      - Bendixen, Bernard
      - Langer, H.
      - Diplomat
      - Sousa, Jaime de
      - Portugal Prisoners Association, Lisbon
      - Ruche, Christian
      - Falcao e Cunha
      - Rodrigues, Adriano
      - Montgomery
      - Costa Lobo, Albano
      - Fernandes, Sergio
      - Costa Gomes, General
      - Garibaldi, Jose
      - Tito de Morais, A.
      - Zenha, Salgado
      - Balsemao, Francisco
      - Gremio
      - Sithole, Valentine
      - Tsung Hsiang
      - British diplomat, Lusaka
      - Chissano, Joaquim
      - Rebelo, Jorge
    - A16-A17, (1974-1975)
      - Sacrame, Satta
      - Diplomat, Lusaka
      - Sousa, Jaime de
      - Jardim, J.
      - Bendixen, Bernard
      - Proensa, J. M. da
      - Alves, Major Vitor
      - Silvera Pinheiro, Commander Serafin
      - Garibaldi, J.
      - Mendonsa, J. M. de
      - Fernandes, Sergio
      - Tito de Morais, A.
      - Ferreira da Cunha, Col.
      - Falcao e Cunha
      - Campos Costa
      - Diaz, Vito
      - Ferreira da Cunha, Col.
      - Balsemao, Francisco
      - Lima, Santos
      - Ferreira, Mario
      - MES representatives
      - Cruz, Brago da
      - Unknown
      - Unknown
      - Costa Lobo, A.
      - Tito de Morais, A.
      - "Kraque" (PRP/Revolutionary Brigades spokesperson)
      - Silva, H. de
      - Member, 5th Division, Lisbon
      - MRPP representative
      - "Kraque"
      - Melo, Antonio
      - Mateus, Rui
      - Cabrita, Joao
    - A18, (1975-1976)
      - Cruz, Brago da
      - Mateus, Rui
      - Fontes, Castro
      - Sousa, Jaime de
      - Chief organizer of the PPD in Northern Portugal
      - PRP/Revolutionary Brigades spokeman
      - Balseamo, Francisco
      - Ferreira de Cunha, Col.
      - Bremner, A.
      - Journalists at Expresso
      - Montgomery
      - Garibaldi, Jose
      - Melo, Antonio
      - Journalist at Expresso
      - Sousa, Jaime de
      - Cunha Leal
      - West German diplomat
      - Veloso, Pires, Brigadier
    - A19, (1976)
      Conditions Governing Access note
      Use copy reference number: 77036_a_0005927 (?)
      - Jardin, J.
      - Sousa, Jaime de
      - Rosa Coutinho, Admiral
      - Mateus, Rui
      - Balseamo, Francisco
      - Sampaio, Dr. Jorge
      - Pires, Antonio
      - Garibaldi, Jose
      - Ribeira da Cunha, Alexander
    - A20, (1976)
      - Avouca, Domingos
      - Didier, Carlos
      - Ferreira da Cunha, Col.
      - Crespo, Vitor
      - Goncalves, General Vasco
    - A21, (1976)
      - Mosimba, T.
      - Kiondo, D.
      - Rodrigues, Adriano
      - Rita-Ferreira, Antonio
      - Norton de Matos
      - Ferreira, Felipe
      - Braganca, Acquino de
      - Magaia, Daniel
      - CID officer
      - Ferreira, Captain
      - British pilot working for Tanzanian government
      - Wicken, Joan
      - Ginwallah, Franny
      - Ganhao, Fernando
      - Parkin, Neville
    - A22, (1976)
      - Belinski, R.
      - Heffer, N.
      - Fleischer, J.
      - Barratt, John
      - Norman, E.
      - Olivier, Harry
      - Carson, John
      - Christie, Ian
      - Trecham, J.
      - Machel (speech to party leaders, Matola, Moz.)
      - Reis, D.
      - Overly, James
      - Braun, F.
      - Engineer at Cabora Bassa
      - Fonseca, C. A.
      - Matsinya, Mariano
      - Rose, A.
      - Magalhaes, Luis
    - A23, (1976)
      - Gates, R.
      - Greek expatriate
      - East German diplomat, Maputo
      - Chinese diplomat, Maputo
      - Branquino, Jose
- EUROPE - COMMUNIST PARTIES (Group B)
  - Notes to tapes B1-B15 (Box 8)
  - Tapes (Box 9)
    - B1-B6 (PCI, 1977-1979)
    - B6-B8 (PCE, 1977-1978)
    - B8-B10 (PCP, 1977-1980)
    - B10-B14 (PCF, 1977-1978)
    - B14-B15 (PCP, 1981)
- GREAT BRITAIN (Group C)
  - Notes to tapes (Box 10)
    - C1
    - C2-C3
    - C4
    - C5
    - C6-C10
    - C11-C15
    - C16-C18
    - C19
    - C20-C22
  - Tapes
    - C1
      - Plowden
      - Roll
      - Franks, Lord
    - C2
      - Franks, Lord
      - Sherfield, Lord
      - Roberthall, Lord
      - Morrison, Sir Nicholas
    - C3
      - Morrison, Sir Nicholas
      - Rickett, Sir Dennis
      - Barnes, Sir Denis
      - Catherwood, Sir Fred
      - Jones, Aubrey
    - C4
      - Smith, Douglas
      - Clucas, Sir Kenneth
      - Brown, Philip
    - C5
      - Brown, Philip
      - Part, Sir Anthony
      - Carey, Sir Peter
      - Wass, Sir Douglas
    - C6
      - Wass, Sir Douglas
      - Rawlinson, Sir Anthony
      - Airey, Sir Laurence
      - Allen, Sir Douglas (Lord Croham)
    - C7 (Box 11)
      - Allen, Sir Douglas (Lord Croham)
      - Berrill, Sir Kenneth
      - Walters, Alan
      - Bancroft, Sir Ian
    - C8
      - Bancroft, Sir Ian
      - Pliatzky, Sir Leo
      - Burney, Sir Anthony
      - Fulton, Lord
      - Renton, Timothy
      - Hordern, Peter
      - Gilmour, Sir Ian
      - Healey, Sir Denis
      - Wilson, Sir Harold
    - C9
      - Wilson, Sir Harold
      - Shore, Peter
      - Diamond, Lord
      - Lever, Lord
      - Thorneycroft, Lord
      - Joseph, Sir Keith
      - Marsh, Sir Richard
      - Robens, Lord
      - Stewart, Lord
      - Benn, Tony
    - C10
      - Benn, Tony
      - Watkinson, Lord
      - Fraser, Lord
      - Zuckerman, Lord
      - Albu, Austen
      - Aldington, Lord
      - Lord Scarman
    - C11
      - Donaldson, Lord (Sir) John
      - Gardiner, Lord
      - Shawcross, Lord
      - Devlin, Lord
      - Barry, John
      - Lewin, Admiral Sir Terence
      - Carver, Field Marshal Lord
    - C12
      - Carver, Field Marshal Lord
      - R. H.
      - White, Sir Dick
      - Fulkener, Sir Eric
      - Cobbold, Lord
    - C13
      - Cobbold, Lord
      - Bolton, Sir George
      - Cromer, Lord
      - Hollom, Sir Jasper
      - Keith, Sir Kenneth (Lord)
      - Benson, Lord
    - C14
      - Keith, Sir Kenneth (Lord)
      - Hopkinson, David
      - Lucas, John
      - Rose, Harold
      - Morse, Jeremy
      - Lloyd, Richard
      - Broadley, Robin
      - Goodison, Sir Nicholas
    - C15
      - Goodison, Sir Nicholas
      - Hamilton, Dundas
      - Murray, Lionel (Lord)
    - C16
      - Murray, Lionel (Lord)
      - Urwin, Harry
      - Cannell, Mike
      - Jones, Jack
      - Chappell, Frank (Lord)
      - Graham, Ken
    - C17
      - Mills, Leif
      - Lea, David
      - Laird, Gavid
      - Drain, Geoffrey
      - Kendall, Bill
    - C18
      - Kendall, Bill
      - Grantham, Roy
      - Lyons, John
      - Basnett, David
      - Mortimer, Jim
      - Nicholas, Sir Harry
      - Frodsham, Anthony
      - Pennock, Sir Raymond
      - Beckett, Sir Terence
    - C19
      - Chandler, Sir Geoffrey
      - MacDougall, Sir Donald
      - Figgures, Sir Frank
      - Mackintosh, Sir Ronald
      - Shone, Sir Robert
    - C20
      - Fraser, T. C.
      - Ezra, Sir Derek
      - Swinden, Alan
      - Parlew, Sir Peter
      - Tombs, Sir Francis
      - Kearkem, Lord
      - Jawett, Sir Alex
    - C21
      - Jawett, Sir Alex
      - Knight, Sir Arthur
      - Garret, John
      - Beeching, Lord
      - Hill, Herbert
      - Villiers, Sir Charles
      - Claphan, Sir Michael
      - Partridge, Sir John
      - Bolton, John E.
      - Murphy, Sir Leslie
      - Stone, David
    - C22
      - Stone, David
      - Morris, Derek
      - McGregor, Peter